Guide to the Propaganda Poster Collection 1914-1996
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Propaganda Poster Collection
1914-1996
bulk 1914-1945
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives and Special Collections
SC 005
8 Oversize drawers 517 Items
This collection contains 517 posters, most issued by governments to influence behavior and public morale. Most items are from the period beginning with the start of World War I and concluding with the end of World War II.
Prior to the advent of broadcast radio and television, governments looked to other media to communicate information to their citizens. One of the most eye-catching formats is the propaganda poster, the use of which peaked during World War I and remained pervasive through World War II. The U.S. government alone produced an estimated 20,000,000 copies of more than 2,500 distinct posters during the First World War. Through these "weapons on the wall," governments persuaded their citizens to participate in a variety of patriotic functions, from purchasing war bonds to conserving scarce resources. These posters also strengthened public support for the wars by providing "message control" about the government's allies and enemies.
Many terms historically used to describe individuals and communities with disabilities are offensive and were used to dismiss, discount and dehumanize these individuals and communities. Terms often focused on a perceived impairment and not the person. MASC recognizes the harm caused by these terms. We retain the language in this finding aid to document history and preserve context.
This collection contains 517 posters, most issued by governments to influence behavior and public morale. Most items are from the period beginning with the start of World War I and concluding with the end of World War II.
The posters found here were collected by the Washington State University Libraries, dating back into the 1910s. They became part of the College's War Library, a collection established in 1937-1938, consisting of rare books, pamphlets, posters, and other ephemera. The collection continued to grow through donations from various sources. In 2009, approximately 300 posters were assembled into this collection. In 2013, approximately 200 more posters were added to the collection. Dating largely from World War II and post-World War II, most of the added posters are in French and are directed toward Parisians, announcing war updates and requesting public action. The additions also include United States World War I and World War II posters, and Russian post-World War I posters.
Poster titles were transcribed from the item, where no title was available, one was created by the collection processors, Amy Sabourin and Morgan Clendenning, and is shown in brackets.
English translations were supplied by collection processor, Amy Sabourin.
Series 1: Propaganda Posters (Russia, South America, Europe, Canada), 1914-1996
Subseries 1.1: Russian Language Posters, 1917-1996
Subseries 1.2: South American Posters, World War I, 1914-1918
Subseries 1.3: European Posters, World War I, 1914-1918
Subseries 1.4: Canadian Posters, World War I, circa 1914-1918
Series 2: Propaganda Posters (United States), World War I, circa 1914-1920
Subseries 2.1: Food Conservation and Material Donations, 1914-1919
Subseries 2.2: Financial Aid: War Savings Stamps, 1914-1918
Subseries 2.3: Financial Aid: Red Cross, 1914-1918
Subseries 2.4: Financial Aid: War Bonds, 1914-1919
Subseries 2.5: Financial Aid: United War Work Campaign, Y.M.C.A, Y.W.C.A; 1914-1919
Series 3: Propaganda Posters (United States), World War II, 1939-1949
Subseries 3.1: Food and Resource Conservation, 1939-1945
Subseries 3.2: Financial Aid: War Bonds, 1939-1945
Subseries 3.3: Public Morale, 1942-1945
Subseries 3.4: Military Recruitment and Training Aids, 1939-1949
Subseries 3.5: Public Information and Safety, 1942-1944
Series 4: International Relations Propaganda Posters (United States and International), World War II, 1939-1945
Series 5: Propaganda Posters (France), World War II and Post World War II, 1939-1960
Subseries 5.1: French World War II, 1939-1945
Subseries 5.2: French Post-World War II, 1943-1955
Series 6: Miscellaneous, 1914-1990
The collection is arranged in six series; three of these are further divided into subseries.
A digital collection containing all items, except number 94 (which was too large to scan), was created in January of 2013. This can be viewed as the Propaganda Poster Digital Collection.
This collection is open and available for research use.
The Washington State University Libraries acquired these posters from various sources during the 20th century. Approximately 300 posters were initially assembled into this collection in 2009. In 2013, a group of approximately 200 more posters were processed and integrated into the collection.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
American Library Association. Library War Service
World War, 1914-1918 -- Posters; World War, 1914-1918 -- United States -- Posters; World War, 1914-1918 -- Europe -- Posters; World War, 1939-1945 -- Posters; World War, 1939-1945 -- United States -- Posters; World War, 1939-1945 -- Europe -- Posters; World War, 1914-1918 -- Propaganda; World War, 1939-1945 -- Propaganda
Military; Political Campaigns; Media and Communications
- Series 1: Propaganda Posters (Russia, South America, Europe, Canada),1914-1996
  - Subseries 1.1: Russian Language Posters, 1917-1996
    - Russia: Images Of A Revolution, 1917-1924, 1983 September 19-October 31; English; 28 x 43 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Holland Library, Washington State University (Folder 1, Item 1)
      Advertisement for an exhibit at the Holland Library about the Russian Revolution.
    - [Untitled Russian Poster 1], circa 1917-1924; Russian; 47.5 x 65.5 cm. Black and white with red accents.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 1, Item 2)
      Poster featuring Russian language text with a quote at the top.
    - [Female Russian Worker Points the Way], circa 1917-1924; Russian; 48 x 66 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 1, Item 3)
      Propaganda poster portraying a female worker pointing emphatically to a row of factory smoke stacks.
    - [Patriotic Russians], circa 1917-1924; Russian; 66 x 48 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 1, Item 4)
      Propaganda poster featuring a group of smiling women carrying flags and dressed in red, white, and blue.
    - [An Announcement to the Workers], circa 1917-1924; Russian; 48 x 66 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 1, Item 5)
      Propaganda poster showing a female worker holding an ad poster with a long line of female workers walking from the factories to the countryside with signs lifted up.
    - [Russian Engineering], 1934; Russian; 48 x 66 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 2, Item 6)
      Propaganda poster showing two workers discussing plans for a piece of machinery. In the background are images of people shooting guns and a presentation scene.
    - [The Physical Fitness of Russia], 1933; Russian; 48 x 66 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 2, Item 7)
      Propaganda poster featuring images of young athletes performing various physical activities.
    - [The People's Uprising], 1920; Russian; 52 x 73.5 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 2, Item 8)
      Propaganda poster with graphic of workers marching with flags and farming equipment. At the base of the image are images of a crown, royal seal, and a pile of gold.
    - [Apocalyptic Message], 1920; Russian; 52 x 73.5 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 2, Item 9)
      Propaganda poster with graphic of a man on a winged red horse flying over a Russian village in a flaming sky. The man is shown holding a torch and an open book.
    - [Communist Takeover], circa 1917-1924; Russian; 53.5 x 73.5 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 2, Item 10)
      Propaganda poster with graphic portraying two men on a winged horse in front of a red star with an image of an army surrounding a burning city.
    - New Russian Art, 1994; English; 61 x 86 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: University of Oklahoma. (Folder 3, Item 11)
      Poster advertising an exhibition of paintings from the Christian Keesee Collection at the Fred Jones Jr. Museum of Art at the University of Oklahoma. Featured on the poster is a work by Sergei Mironenko titled, Goodbye.
    - [Untitled Russian Poster 2], 1996; Russian; 59 x 89.5 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 3, Item 12)
      Poster featuring a series of quotations in the Russian language.
    - [Russian Propaganda Poster], 1932; Russian; 140 x 69 cm. Black, red, and white.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 3, Item 12.11)
      Portrays a series of photographs and drawings. Includes a large cutout of a man to the far left of the poster, surrounded by crowds and lines of people. In the center of the poster is a portion of a map of Russia with a red shape flowing over much of the
    - [Papal Poster], circa 1920-1935; Russian; 49 x 63 cm. Yellow background with black and white graphic.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 3, Item 12.12)
      Propaganda poster featuring a graphic of a religious figure pointing upward while holding onto a creature with pig limbs, a skirt, and a large bucket over its head.
    - [WWI Destruction Poster], 1931; Russian; 71 x 104 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 3, Item 12.13)
      Poster features a man walking out of view. Within his five footprints are scenes relating to religion, war, Nazism, and death that are associated with WWI and its repercussions.
    - [Twelve Segmented Russian Drawings], 1932; Russian; 143 x 103.5 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 3, Item 12.14)
      Consists of twelve numbered drawings that are separated by black lines. The images range from realistic to cartoon, and consist of depictions of everyday life, as well as abstract ideas. The final image, number twelve, is the largest and illustrates a man
    - [Three Men Angry with Stalin], 1932; Russian; 92 x 70 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 3, Item 12.15)
      Propaganda poster illustrating three men, one with a swastika on his coat. The focus of their anger is upon a parade featuring a banner with the face of Joseph Stalin and "15 October."
    - [Angel Placed on a Serving Dish], 1932; Russian; 101 x 74 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 3, Item 12.16)
      Russian poster with the graphic of a man dressed as a waiter, presenting a serving platter with an angel placed on top. The angel has a sword stuck in its stomach and is pink with yellow hair. Bloody handprints are on the cloth the man holds, and there is
    - [Russian Factory Laborers], 1932; Russian; 71 x 105 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 3, Item 12.17)
      Consists of a chart surrounded by photographs of individuals working in a variety of factory settings.
    - [Stalin and Others Surrounded by Russian Achievements], 1932; Russian; 62.5 x 69.5 cm. Black, red, and white.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 3, Item 12.18)
      Located in the center of the poster are graphics of Joseph Stalin with other significant men. Around them all are red images of fields, factories, and armies.
    - [Sailor Observing Aircrafts], 1932; Russian; 54 x 75 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 3, Item 12.19)
      Poster illustrating a single sailor standing on a ship, observing a squadron of airplanes through binoculars.
    - [Stomping on Religious Men], 1930; Russian; 51 x 70 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 3, Item 12.20)
      Propaganda poster portraying a large black boot stepping upon a group of men representing a variety of religions, each illustrated with a halo around his head. One man is straddled on top of the boot with the intention of shinning it.
  - Subseries 1.2: South American Posters, World War I, 1914-1918
    - La Cruz Roja (Ecuador), circa 1914-1918; Spanish; 53.5 x 79 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: The Red Cross. (Folder 4, Item 13)
      Promotional poster for the Red Cross in Ecuador. Graphic shows the American flag crossed with the Ecuadorian flag.
    - La Cruz Roja (Peru), circa 1914-1918; Spanish; 53.5 x 79 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: The Red Cross. (Folder 4, Item 14)
      Promotional poster for the Red Cross in Peru. Graphic shows the American flag crossed with the Peruvian flag. English Translation: "The Red Cross, Mother of All the Nations"..."Emblems of Liberty and of Humanity."
    - La Cruz Roja (Dominican Republic), circa 1914-1918; Spanish; 53.5 x 79 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: The Red Cross. (Folder 4, Item 15)
      Promotional poster for the Red Cross in the Dominican Republic. Graphic shows the American flag crossed with the flag of the Dominican Republic. English Translation: "The Red Cross, Mother of All the Nations"..."Emblems of Liberty and of Humanity."
    - La Cruz Roja (Brazil), circa 1914-1918; Spanish; 53.5 x 79 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: The Red Cross. (Folder 4, Item 16)
      Promotional poster for the Red Cross in Brazil. Graphic shows the American flag crossed with the Brazilian flag. English Translation: "The Red Cross, Mother of All the Nations"..."Emblems of Liberty and of Humanity."
  - Subseries 1.3: European Posters, World War I, 1914-1918
    - L'Italia, 1917; Italian; 52.5 x 71 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: George Illian. Published by Latham Lith. & Ptg. Co. Brooklyn, New York. (Folder 5, Item 17)
      A reminder that the people of Italy need more meat, wheat, fat, and sugar. English Translation: "Eat less of these foods so they can go to our people and troops."
    - A Message From Poland, circa 1914-1918; Polish; 52 x 71 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: George Illian. (Folder 6, Item 18)
      Polish war propaganda poster asking for the aid of the American people. English Translation: "In America, will you help fight for liberty in Poland? Eat less!"
    - Où l'Héroïsme Redevient Femme, circa 1914-1918; French; 26 x 37.5 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 7, Item 19)
      Propaganda poster featuring a cartoon depicting a nurse standing on a chair in terror from a mouse on the floor. The medicine she was to administer is lying on the floor. English Translation: "Where heroism returns to normalcy for the average woman"..."Evid
    - Aux Meres, Aux Veuves, circa 1914-1918; French; 29 x 44 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Geoffroy. Printed by P. Schneider & Cie. Passage du Caire, Paris. (Folder 7, Item 20)
      Propaganda poster featuring a cartoon depicting death strangling a German soldier. English Translation: "To the mothers, To the widows"..."Oh! I will finish well by having you too, William!"
    - Vers l'Intervention, circa 1914-1918; French; 54 x 38 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: Abel Truchet. (Folder 7, Item 21)
      Propaganda poster featuring a sketch of two German officers looking across a body of water at a smoking volcano.
    - Printemps, circa 1914-1918; French; 53.5 x 38 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: Abel Truchet. (Folder 7, Item 22)
      Propaganda poster featuring a sketch of old man surveying a battlefield with crows perched nearby on a dead tree. English Translation: "Springtime"..."How black the nightingales are this year!"
    - En Champagne, circa 1914-1918; French; 54 x 38 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: Abel Truchet. (Folder 7, Item 23)
      Propaganda poster featuring a sketch of German officer surveying a vineyard field. English Translation: "In Champagne"..."If, at least, they would have planted all this with potatoes!"
    - Les Laches, circa 1914-1918; French; 54 x 38 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: Abel Truchet. (Folder 7, Item 24)
      Propaganda poster featuring a sketch of a submarine sailor using a telescope to look at an approaching ship. English Translation: "The Cowards"..."Damn! It seems to me that the captain has a gun!!!!"
    - l'Occupation Allemande en Belgique, 1915; French; 54.5 x 43 cm. Black and white with color highlights.; Creator/Publisher: Auguste-Lucien Bognard. (Folder 7, Item 25)
      Propaganda poster featuring a sketch of two Belgian children mocking a German soldier while he posts a proclamation. English Translation: "The German Occupation in Belgium"..."The Proclamation of the Governor...the Effects!"..."Dedicated to our little armies of
    - 1914, N/A; 30.5 x 44.5 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: Raoul Uion. (Folder 7, Item 26)
      Propaganda poster featuring a charcoal drawing depicting two angelic beings carrying the flags of Britain and France in pursuit of a German officer who leaves a trail of crosses in his wake. The artist was inspired by a painting by Pierre-Paul Prud'hon ti
    - [Refugees in the Street], 1915; N/A; 50 x 40 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Henry de Groux. Engraved by Devambez. (Folder 7, Item 27)
      Propaganda poster featuring a pastel chalk image depicting a street full of weary refugees, probably somewhere in France.
    - La Horde, circa 1914-1918; N/A; 40 x 53 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 7, Item 28)
      Propaganda poster featuring a charcoal drawing depicting a young girl lying in the street in a puddle of blood while a line of troops marches by.
    - Le Kas Allemand, circa 1914-1918; French; 42 x 28 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Creator Unidentified. Printed at 99 Boulevard Raspail, Paris. (Folder 8, Item 29)
      An anti-German war poster making fun of the German use of the letter "k" in places where it does not belong. English Translation: "The German K", "By a phenomenon as yet unexplained, the German Alphabet only understands a single letter: K."
    - Pour La Belle Terre De France, circa 1914-1918; French; 41.5 x 29 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Benito. (Folder 8, Item 30)
      Public announcement to the people of France with graphic depicting farm workers in the fields waving to American soldiers marching past. English Translation: "For the Beautiful Land of France"... "French countrymen, let's greet the free American soldiers wh
    - La Grande Guerre, 1914 October; French; 41.5 x 28 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Creator Unidentified. Printed at 13, Quai d'Anjou, Paris. (Folder 8, Item 31)
      Propaganda poster featuring graphic illustrating the story of a merciful Russian stretcher bearer who saved the lives of injured German soldiers from a vicious wolf attack in the woods of Augustow. English Translation (of title): "The Great War."
    - Le Coeur de l'Amerique, circa 1914-1918; French; 41 x 29.5 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Benito. American Red Cross. (Folder 8, Item 32)
      Propaganda poster featuring graphic illustrating the service and character of the American Red Cross to the people of France. English Translation: "The Heart of America"..."In the interior as with the soldiers, no sufferance is left unattended by the Americ
    - Mobilisation Des Détenus Allemands (Juillet 1914), 1914 October; French; 45 x 31 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: Creator Unidentified. Printed by the Librarie de l'Estampe, 68, Chaussée d'Antin, Paris. (Folder 8, Item 33)
      Propaganda poster featuring an illustrated dialogue between a group of freed German prisoners and their head officers. English Translation: "Mobilization of German Detainees (July 1914)"... "What did you do to deserve your imprisonment?"..."What! You don't re
    - Le Vin Chaud, circa 1914-1918; French; 79 x 120 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: French Ministry of Agriculture. (Folder 8, Item 34)
      French propaganda poster featuring graphic of a map of France with four individuals standing within and drinking cups of hot wine together. English Translation: "Hot Wine, From the Back to the Front...We will overcome in drinking it!"
    - Britishers Enlist To-Day, circa 1914-1918; English; 102 x 69 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Guy Lipscombe; The Hegeman Print N.Y. (Folder 8, Item 34.5)
      Enlistment poster featuring a British flag.
  - Subseries 1.4: Canadian Posters, World War I, circa 1914-1918
    - Naval Service of Canada, circa 1914-1918; English; 107 x 70.5 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Canadian Department of Naval Service. (Folder 9, Item 35)
      Canadian naval recruitment poster advertising vacancies for seaman class boys, stokers, and other various trades. Desirable candidates are described as: "Only strong, healthy and well educated men and boys are required and they must be of good character."
- Series 2: Propaganda Posters (United States),World War I, circa 1914-1920
  - Subseries 2.1: Food Conservation and Material Donations, 1914-1919
    - Books For Our Soldiers And Sailors, circa 1914-1918; English; 35.5 x 28 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: Unidentified (Folder 10, Item 36)
      Poster labeling an appropriate drop-off point for donated books. Poster also reminds the audience that donated books will be accepted at the public library.
    - [Do The Jackies Want Books?], circa 1914-1918; English; 25.5 x 38 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: American Library Association, Library War Service. (Folder 10, Item 37)
      Promotional poster for the Library War Service showing images of soldiers reading books that were provided by the American Library Association. (2 copies)
    - [A.L.A. Camp Libraries], circa 1914-1918; English; 38 x 51.5 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: American Library Association, Library War Service. (Folder 10, Item 38)
      Promotional poster for the Library War Service showing images of soldiers reading books that were provided by the American Library Association.
    - [The A.L.A. Library Reading Porch], circa 1914-1918; English; 38 x 51.5 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: American Library Association, Library War Service. (Folder 10, Item 39)
    - [A Corner In Books], circa 1914-1918; English; 50.5 x 77 cm. Black and white.; Creator/Publisher: American Library Association, Library War Service. (Folder 10, Item 40)
    - [Special War Libraries for our Fighting Men], 1918; English; 65 x 52 cm. White background with green lettering.; Creator/Publisher: American Library Association, Library War Service. (Folder 10, Item 41)
      A map of the United States featuring dots representing the locations of each "War Library" set up by the American Library Association.
    - Knowledge Wins, circa 1914-1918; English; 48 x 71 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Dan Smith. American Library Association. Designed and printed by Thomsen-Ellis Company: Baltimore and New York. (Folder 10, Item 42)
      A reminder to American citizens that public library books are free and that knowledge will help win the war. Graphic shows soldier climbing from the trenches onto a pathway of books leading to a U.S. city skyline. (2 copies)
    - Hey Fellows!, 1918; English; 50.5 x 76 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: John E. Sheridan. American Library Association. Printed by the American Lithographic Co., N.Y. (Folder 10, Item 43)
      Poster for the United War Work Campaign showing a sailor reading, and above him a soldier reminds the public that donations help soldiers receive the books they need. Stamped by the Committee on Public Information Division of Pictorial Publicity.
    - Books Wanted, circa 1917; English; 71 x 106.5 cm. Color.; Creator/Publisher: Charles Buckles Falls. American Library Association. (Folder 10, Item 44)
      Poster reminding citizens of the need for books for soldiers overseas and encouraging them to bring their donations to the local public library.